Harry Emerson Wildes Papers
Harry Emerson Wildes Papers
1945-1953
Wildes, Harry Emerson, 1890-1982
3.5 linear ft.
American sociologist, biographer, political advisor to the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers (SCAP). Collection consists entirely of reports on post-World War II Japan.
3175656
Biographical History
Harry Emerson Wildes (1890-1982) was an American sociologist and biographer. Among his best-known works are biographies of William Penn, George Fox and Anthony Wayne. During and after World War II he served as a political advisor to the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers (SCAP), which was both the title held by General Douglas MacArthur and the collective name of his administrative office during the occupation of Japan (it was usually referred to in Japan as General Headquarters or GHQ). Wildes contributed to the drafting of the Japanese Constitution, drawing on the constitutions of other countries including the United States, France, Germany, and the Soviet Union.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harry Emerson Wildes Papers consists of reports and miscellaneous other documents generated for the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers (SCAP), most of them focused on post-World War II Japan. There is one item by Wildes that was published in a
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Politics, government and public administration; Wildes, Harry Emerson, 1890-1982.; Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers.; Historians -- Japan.; Historians -- United States.; Public health -- Japan.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Occupied territories,; Japan -- History -- Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Japan -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989.; Administrative reports.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Chronologies.; Government records.; Official reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harry Emerson Wildes, 1964.
Inventory
- Reports
  - Articles covering the five major Japanese political parties, Sep 1946; series of reports compiled by SCAP's Political Parties Branch, Public Administration Division, Government Section (Box 1)
  - Catalog of administrative directives to the Japanese government, Volume I, Apr 1947; also called "SCAPIN-A's"; contains SCAPIN-A #1-2000, also cover only for Volume IV (Box 1)
  - Civil Historical Section, Political and Social Affairs Division, miscellaneous, Jul-Sep 1950; reports on Japanese arts, culture, events; includes bibliographies, chronologies, summaries of movies and films, etc. (Box 1)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan & Korea, No.'s 1-3, Sep-Dec 1945; 3 volumes in 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan & Korea, No.'s 4-5, Jan-Feb 1946; 2 volumes in 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan, No.'s 6-9, Mar-Jun 1946; title changed with this volume; 4 volumes in 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan, No.'s 10-16, Jul 1946-Jan 1947; 7 volumes in 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan, No.'s 17-22, Feb-Jul 1947; 7 volumes in 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan, No.'s 23-27, Aug-Dec 1947; 5 volumes in 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan, No.'s 28-32, Jan-May 1948; 5 volumes in 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Summation of non-military activities in Japan, No.'s 33-35, Jun-Aug 1948; 3 volumes in 3 folders (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Index of JCS directives to Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Dec 1948 (Box 7)
  - Post-war public health developments, by Harry Emerson Wildes, 1953; reprint from Contemporary Japan, Vol. XXI, Nos. 10-12; 3 copies (Box 7)
  - Stylebook, Civil Historical Section, Nov 1950; outline, purpose, typing style and formatting, etc. (Box 7)